Joseph A. Smith Papers
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Joseph A. Smith Papers.
1983-2002.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Smith, Joseph A.; Smith, Jos. A.
491 linear feet.
Joseph A[nthony] Smith, children's author/illustrator and artist received his BFA from the Pratt Institute in 1960, where he began teaching in 1961. He continues to teach there in the Department of Painting and Drawing. The collection contains artwork for over thirty children's books.
MSS19970066
Biography
Joseph A[nthony] Smith was born in Bellefonte, Pennsylvania in 1936. He studied with Hobson Pittman at the Pennsylvania State University from 1955-1957 and received his BFA from the Pratt Institute in 1960, where he began teaching in 1961. He continues to teach there in the Department of Painting and Drawing.
Smith has also worked as a professional artist since 1961. He has exhibited his work at the Pennsylvania Academy for Fine Arts (1961, 1967, 1969), at the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences (1966), at the Bethel Gallery in Connecticut (1978), at the Newhouse Gallery in Staten Island (1982), at Adirondak Community College in New York ( 1987), at the Trenton City Museum (1992), at the Staemfli Gallery in New York (1992), at the Esther Allen Green Museum in Ohio, and at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center in Connecticut (2004). Though these exhibitions were independent, Smith has also worked extensively with other artists. Smith has also employed his art by working as a design consultant, an exhibition designer, and a member of the Board of Directors on the Staten Island Council of Arts (1971-1976).
Smith's art has been recognized by his peers with several prestigious awards, including the Mary S. Litt Award for Watercolor, 100th Annual American Watercolor Society (1967) and the New York Society of Illustrators Merit Award (1973, 1974, 1979, 1982, 1998).
Bunton, Donald, Jr., et al., Who's Who in American Art: 2001-2002, New Providence, New Jersey, Marquis Who's Who, 2001. 1116.
Published Works:
Books by Smith
The Pen and Ink Book: Materials and Techniques for Today's Artist. Watson-Guptill Publications, 1992.
Circus Train. Harry N. Abrams, 2001.
Books Illustrated by Smith.
Martin, Bill, Knots on a Counting Rope, Holt, Rinehart, and Winston, 1966.
Epstein, Sam and Beryl Williams Epstein, European Folk Festivals, Garrard Publishing Company, 1968.
Conrad, Joseph, Heart of Darkness and Other Tales, Franklin Library, 1982.
Evslin, Bernard, Hercules., Morrow, 1984 .Trumpet Club, 1991.
Hautzig, Deborah, and Frank L. Baum, The Wizard of Oz, Random House, 1984.
MacDonald, George, The Princess and the Goblin, Grosset and Dunlap, 1985 .Scholastic, 1990.
McKinley, Robin, and Rudyard Kipling, Tales from the Jungle Book, Random House, 1985.
Segel, Elizabeth, Short Takes: A Short Story Collection for Young Readers, Lothrop, Lee, and Shepard Books, 1986 .Dell Publishing, 1992.
Overton, Jenny, The Thirteen Days of Christmas, Greenwillow Books, 1987.
Guiberson, Brenda Z., Turtle People, Atheneum Books, 1990.
Cooper, Susan, Matthew's Dragon, M.K. McElderry Books, 1990 .Aladdin Books, 1994.
Banks, Lynne Reid, The Adventures of King Midas, Morrow Junior Books, 1992.
Fleishman, Sid, Jim Ugly, Greenwillow Books, 1992 .Harper Trophy, 2003.
Griffith, Helen V., "Mine Will," Said John, Greenwillow Books, 1992.
Serfozo, Mary, Benjamin Bigfoot, M.K. McElderry Books, 1993.
Hass, Jessie, Chipmunk!, Greenwillow Books, 1993.
Cooper, Susan, Danny and the Kings, Margaret K. McElderry Books, 1993.
Jones, Diana Wynne, Stopping for a Spell: Three Fantasies, Greenwillow Books, 1993 .Puffin Books, 1996.
Haas, Jessie, Mowing, Greenwillow Books, 1994.
Levin, Betty, Starshine and Sunglow, Greenwillow Books, 1994.
Wolkstein, Diane, Step by Step, Morrow Junior Books, 1994 .Harcourt, 2000.
Whitcraft, Melissa, Tales from One Street Over, Avon Books, 1994.
Haas, Jessie, A Blue for Beware, Greenwillow Books, 1995.
Heller, Nicholas, Goblins in Green, Greenwillow Books, 1995 .Mulberry Books, 1999.
Gellman, Mark, and Thomas Hartman, How Do You Spell God?: Answers to the Big Questions from Around the World, Morrow Junior Books, 1995 .Beech Tree, 1998.
Haas, Jessie, No Foal Yet, Greenwillow Books, 1995.
Haas, Jessie, Be Well, Beware, Greenwillow Books, 1996.
Levin, Betty, Gift Horse, Greenwillow Books, 1996 .Scholastic, 1997.
Farmer, Nancy, Runnery Granary, Greenwillow Books, 1996.
Haas, Jessie, Sugaring, Greenwillow Books, 1996.
Ginsburg, Mirra, Clay Boy, Greenwillow Books, 1997.
Heller, Nicholas, The Giant, Greenwillow Books, 1997.
Fleischman, Sid, Bandit's Moon, Greenwillow Books, 1998.
Huck, Charlotte H., A Creepy Countdown, Greenwillow Books, 1998.
Levin, Betty, Creature Crossing, Greenwilow Books, 1999.
Heller, Nicholas, Ogres! Ogres! Ogres!, Greenwillow Books, 1999 .Scholastic 2000.
Heller, Nicholas, Elwood and the Witch, Greenwillow Books, 2000.
Haas, Jessie, Hurry!, Greenwillow Books, 2000.
Rubin, Susan Goldman, The Yellow House: Vincent van Gogh and Paul Gauguin Side by Side, Harry N. Abrams, 2001.
Gowler, Rhonda, Eek! Creak! Snicker, Sneak, Atheneum Books for Young Readers, 2002.
Armstrong, Jennifer, Audubon: Painter of Birds in the Wild Frontier, H.N. Abrams, 2003.
Jong, Erica, Witches, Harry N. Abrams, 2004.
Scope and Content
The Joseph A. Smith Papers contain work by and documents pertaining to Joseph A. (Jos. A.) Smith's career as an illustrator of children's books. The collection consists, in the main, of original artwork by Smith and color proofs. The contents of the collection date from roughly 1983 to 2002. The majority of the collection dates from the 1990s.
Arrangement
The Joseph A. Smith Papers contains only one series: Children's Literature. The collection does not include any of Joseph A. Smith's works in other genres at this time.
For ease of research, the collection is arranged alphabetically by book title. When necessary, there has been some separation of materials according to physical size. This separation is reflected in the finding aid by box numbers and locations.
Series I: Children's Literature (undated, 1983-2002).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of children's literature artwork and children's literature. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Smith, Joseph A. (Joseph Anthony), 1936-
Subjects:
Children's literature, American Illustrations.; Illustrations of books--United States.; Children's literature--Connecticut illustrators.; Illustrated children's books.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Press releases.; Artwork.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Illustrations.; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Typescripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Sketches.; Drawings.; Speeches.
Occupations:
Illustrator.; Artist.; Author.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions for this collection.
Acquisition Information
The materials in this collection were received from Joseph A. Smith in three installments. The first and largest accession was received in 1997, and two smaller and later donations were received in 2001 and 2003.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Children's Literature, undated, 1983-2002
  - The Adventures of King Midas
    - Black and white illustrations, ca. 1992 (Box 3:, Folder 39)
  - Audubon: Painter of Birds in the Wild Frontier
    - Preliminary artwork, small, ca. 2002 (Box 8:, Folder 64)
    - Partial paste-up dummy, ca. 2002 (Box 8:, Folder 65)
    - Preliminary artwork, large, ca. 2002 (Box 8:, Folder 65a)
    - Artwork, 2002 (Box 8:, Folder 66)
  - Bandit's Moon
    - Cover, undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Cover art, 1997 (Box 8:, Folder 67)
  - Benjamin Bigfoot
    - Sketch dummy, undated (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Copies of dummies and annotations, undated (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, undated (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Color proofs, ca. 1993 (Box 3:, Folder 40)
    - Artwork, 1992 (Box 8:, Folder 68)
    - Jacket proofs, ca. 1993 (Box 8:, Folder 69)
  - Cart and Cwidder
    - Dust jackets, 1995 (Box 3:, Folder 41)
  - Chipmunk
    - Cover Sketch, ca. 1992 July 15 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - Paste-up dummies (2) and copies, ca. 1992 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Color artwork, 1992 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Jacket proofs, ca. 1993 (Box 8:, Folder 70)
    - Color proofs, ca. 1993 (Box 8:, Folder 71)
    - Artwork, 1992 (Box 8:, Folder 72)
  - Circus Train
    - Proofs, ca. 2000 (Box 9:, Folder 73)
    - Paste-up dummy, ca. 2000 (Box 9:, Folder 74)
    - Poster, 2001 (Box 9:, Folder 75)
    - Artwork, 2000 (Box 9:, Folder 76)
  - Clay Boy
    - Dust jacket, ca. 1997 (Box 9:, Folder 77)
    - Color tests, ca. 1996 (Box 9:, Folder 78)
    - Color proofs, 1996 July (Box 9:, Folder 79)
    - Promotional poster, ca. 1997 (Box 9:, Folder 80)
    - Artwork, ca. 1996 (Box 9:, Folder 81)
  - Contrary
    - Artwork, 1990 (Box 10:, Folder 82)
  - Creature Crossing
    - Artwork, 1998 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Cover art, 1998 (Box 3:, Folder 42)
    - Dust jacket, ca. 1999 (Box 10:, Folder 83)
  - A Creepy Countdown
    - Cover mock-up, undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Font sample, undated (Box 4:, Folder 47)
    - Typescript by Charlotte Huck, undated (Box 4:, Folder 48)
    - Small color artwork, undated (Box 4:, Folder 49)
    - Dummy, undated (Box 4:, Folder 50)
    - Black and white sketches, undated (Box 4:, Folder 51)
    - "Halloween Countdown" cover sketches, ca. 1996 (Box 4:, Folder 52)
    - Large color artwork, ca. 1996 (Box 4:, Folder 53)
    - Mounted color artwork, undated (Box 4:, Folder 54)
    - Mounted black and white artwork, pages 1-2, 4-9, 11-12, 1997 (Box 5:, Folder [no folders])
    - Mounted black and white artwork, pages 13-14, 16-24, 1997 (Box 6:, Folder [no folders])
    - Second proofs, ca. 1998 (Box 10:, Folder 84)
    - Third proofs, ca. 1998 (Box 10:, Folder 85)
    - Unidentified proofs, ca. 1998 (Box 10:, Folder 86)
    - Artwork, unnumbered, ca. 1998 (Box 10:, Folder 87)
    - Oversize uncut proofs, ca. 1998 (Box OS:, Folder 148)
    - Jacket proofs, ca. 1998 (Box OS:, Folder 149)
  - Danny and the Kings
    - Copies of paste-up dummies (2), undated (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - Color proofs (partial), ca. 1993 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 1:, Folder 11a)
    - Typescripts, 1992 January (Box 1:, Folder 11b)
    - "The Gift of the Magi" [teleplay], 1990 October (Box 1:, Folder 11c)
    - Color proofs, ca. 1993 (Box 3:, Folder 45)
    - Small artwork, 1992 (Box 3:, Folder 43)
    - Large artwork, 1992 (Box 3:, Folder 44)
    - Dust jacket paste-ups and proofs, ca. 1993 (Box 10:, Folder 88)
    - Uncut proofs, ca. 1993 (Box OS:, Folder 146)
    - Oversize original artwork, 1992 (Box OS:, Folder 147)
  - Elwood and the Witch
    - Color Proofs (1 of 2), 1999 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Color proofs (2 of 2), 1999 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Dust jacket, 1999 (Box 11:, Folder 89)
    - Original artwork, 1999 (Box 11:, Folder 90)
  - The Giant
    - Proofs, ca. 1997 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 11:, Folder 91)
    - Original artwork, 1996 (Box 11:, Folder 92)
    - Dust jacket proofs and color tests, ca. 1996-1997 (Box 11:, Folder 93)
  - Gift Horse
    - Black and white illustrations, 1996 (Box 3:, Folder 46)
  - Goblins in Green
    - Notes, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, undated (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Color proofs, 1994 (Box 7:, Folder 55)
    - Proofs, 1994 (Box 12:, Folder 98)
    - Covers and dust jackets, ca. 1995 (Box 12:, Folder 99)
    - Jacket proofs, ca. 1994-1995 (Box 12:, Folder 100)
    - Poster proofs and posters, 1995 January (Box 12:, Folder 101)
    - Original artwork, 1994 (Box 12:, Folder 102)
  - Greenwillow Books Fact Sheet, ca. 1999 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Hercules
    - Preliminary sketches, ca. 1983 (Box 7:, Folder 56)
    - Pen and ink illustrations, 1983 (Box 7:, Folder 57)
    - Original artwork, 1983 (Box 11:, Folder 94)
  - Hurry!
    - Dummy, ca. 1999 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - Proofs, 2000 (Box 11:, Folder 95)
    - Original artwork, 1999 (Box 11:, Folder 96)
    - Dust jacket, 2000 (Box 11:, Folder 97)
    - Jacket proofs, ca. 2000 (Box OS:, Folder 144)
    - Oversize and uncut proofs, 2000 (Box OS:, Folder 145)
  - Matthew's Dragon
    - Artwork, undated (Box 2:, Folder 19)
    - Original artwork, 1990 (Box 13:, Folder 103)
    - Color proofs, 1991 (Box 13:, Folder 104)
  - "Mine Will," said John
    - Original color art, ca. 1991 (Box 13:, Folder 105)
    - Color proofs, 1991-1992 (Box 13:, Folder 106)
    - Dust jacket and jacket proofs, 1992 (Box 13:, Folder 107)
  - Mowing
    - Typescript by Jessie Haas, undated (Box 2:, Folder 20)
    - Research, undated (Box 2:, Folder 21)
    - Sketches and copies, undated (Box 2:, Folder 22)
    - Paste-up dummies and copies, undated (Box 2:, Folder 23)
    - First proofs, ca. 1994 (Box 14:, Folder 109)
    - Second proofs, ca. 1994 (Box 14:, Folder 110)
    - Jacket and cover proofs, 1994 (Box 14:, Folder 111)
    - Unidentified proofs, ca. 1994 (Box 14:, Folder 112)
    - Original artwork, 1992 (Box 14:, Folder 113)
    - Galleys, ca. 1994 (Box OS:, Folder 142)
  - The Nature of the Beast
    - Original artwork, undated (Box 13:, Folder 108)
  - No Foal Yet
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, undated (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - First proofs, ca. 1995 (Box 15:, Folder 114)
    - Second proofs, ca. 1995 (Box 15:, Folder 115)
    - Unidentified proofs, ca. 1995 (Box 15:, Folder 116)
    - Jacket proofs, ca. 1995 (Box 15:, Folder 117)
    - Original artwork, 1994 (Box 15:, Folder 118)
  - Ogres! Ogres! Ogres!
    - Paste-up cover dummies, undated (Box 16:, Folder 119)
    - First and second proofs, 1999 (Box 16:, Folder 120)
    - Cut proofs, ca. 1999 (Box 16:, Folder 121)
    - Original artwork, 1998 (Box 16:, Folder 122)
    - Oversize uncut proofs, ca. 1999 (Box OS:, Folder 143)
  - Runnery Granary
    - Copies of text and sketches, ca. 1995 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - Ink sketches and copies, 1995 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, undated (Box 2:, Folder 27a)
    - Cover art, 1995 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
    - Cover page plan, ca. 1995 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
    - Proofs, ca. 1996 (Box 2:, Folder 30)
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, ca. 1996 (Box 17:, Folder 123)
    - First proofs, ca. 1996 (Box 17:, Folder 124)
    - Second proofs, ca. 1996 (Box 17:, Folder 125)
    - Jacket proofs, ca. 1996 (Box 17:, Folder 126)
    - Original artwork, 1995 (Box 17:, Folder 127)
  - Starshine and Sunglow
    - Cover art, 1993 (Box 7:, Folder 58)
  - Step by Step
    - Correspondence, 1993 March (Box 2:, Folder 31)
    - Typescript copies, 1993 February (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - Jacket blurbs [t.s. copies], undated (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - Galley copies and transparancies, 1993 January (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - Research for sketches, undated (Box 2:, Folder 35)
    - Sketches, ca. 1993 March (Box 2:, Folder 36)
    - Jacket and cover plans, 1992 November (Box 2:, Folder 37)
    - Partial proofs, ca. 1994 (Box 19:, Folder 133)
    - Galleys, 1992-1993 (Box 19:, Folder 134)
    - Color dummy [incomplete], ca. 1992 (Box 19:, Folder 135)
    - Dust jacket, ca. 1994 (Box 19:, Folder 136)
    - Original artwork, 1993 (Box 19:, Folder 137)
  - Stopping for a Spell
    - Cover art, 1992 (Box 7:, Folder 59)
  - Sugaring
    - Paste-up dummy and copy, undated (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - Turtle People
    - Cover art, undated (Box 7:, Folder 60)
    - First proofs, ca. 1996 (Box 18:, Folder 128)
    - Second proofs, ca. 1996 (Box 18:, Folder 129)
    - Final proofs, 1996 (Box 18:, Folder 130)
    - Jacket proofs, ca. 1996 (Box 18:, Folder 131)
    - Original artwork, 1995 (Box 18:, Folder 132)
  - Tales from the Jungle Book
    - Original artwork, ca. 1985 (Box 20:, Folder 138)
  - Unidentified artwork, 1984-1995 (Box 20:, Folder 139)
  - The Wizard of Oz
    - Original artwork, cover to page 17, ca. 1984 (Box 21)
    - Original artwork, pages 18 to 35, ca. 1984 (Box 22)
    - Original artwork, pages 37 to end, ca. 1984 (Box 23)
  - The Yellow House
    - Mounted pencil sketches, undated (Box 7:, Folder 61)
    - Map copy, undated (Box 7:, Folder 62)
    - Preliminary color artwork, undated (Box 7:, Folder 63)
    - Medium color artwork, undated (Box 24:, Folder 140)
    - Large color artwork, undated (Box 24:, Folder 142)